<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog backup</title>
    <description>Backup blog posts from various blogs.</description>
    <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io</link>
    <atom:link href="http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>What is(n’t) palaeontology like?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/paleontology-300x227.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot;&gt;
After rereading &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/03/14/whats-it-like-to-study-zoology/&quot;&gt;Sive’s excellent blog&lt;/a&gt; post on what is a zoologist or at least what is it like to study it, I remember having a slightly similar difficulty in explaining my background in palaeontology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reactions range from: &amp;quot;Oh... Palaeontology? That’s like the origins of humans and stuff?&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;So you go on excavations and find ancient Roman pottery?&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;Bheuuh, want another beer?&amp;quot;. What frustrated me is that none of these reactions are correct but neither are they totally incorrect (especially the last one!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Palaeontology is not archaeology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people that have only a vague idea of what palaeontology is are usually not big fans of Jurassic Park and don’t know &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dr._Alan_Grant#Dr._Alan_Grant&quot;&gt;Alan Grant&lt;/a&gt; so they usually associate palaeontology with &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ross_Geller&quot;&gt;Ross Geller&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indiana_Jones&quot;&gt;Indiana Jones&lt;/a&gt;. Being not a big fan of TV series, I don’t know whether Ross is a good representation of the reality of life as a palaeontologist but I know that Indiana is not. Not even a little bit. He’s an archaeologist. That might be a nerdy detail for some but to understand what palaeontology is about, it is important to understand the difference. Even though both archaeologists and palaeontologists study the past based on what they find in the ground (and in books!), the time scales involved make the two disciplines impossible to compare. Archaeologists are mainly interested in human culture (they might find animal bones but they are usually the fragments of crafted objects). In contrast, palaeontologists are interested in the remains of life that occurred before human civilisation. Therefore we have two very different time scales here: from years to centuries or, at a push, millennia for archaeologists and from hundreds to millions of millennia (or billion of years) for palaeontologists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Palaeontology is not about excavations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Palaeontologists do not excavate fossils, that’s a job for Oryctologists. Okay, I’m being picky with the terms here but, again, the distinction is important. Most palaeontologists are also oryctologists, meaning that they go into the field and do excavations as the basis for their scientific work (yeah, in the end, that’s not a cliché, one of the nicest parts of the job is field work!). However, not all palaeontologists are oryctologists (even though most are) and many oryctologists are not palaeontologists. Again, palaeontology is not only about digging up fossils and putting them in museums (contrary to what &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=B7zo2zY1Zqg&quot;&gt;this song&lt;/a&gt; suggests), it is about the study of changes that occurred on our planet through deep time (geography, climate, etc...) and how they affected living organisms (evolution, extinction, etc...).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/JP-Digsite-300x164.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we’re on the subject of oryctology, there is a huge public misconception about excavations. Most people that have seen Jurassic Park might think that, in the 90’s, one could just go into the field armed with nothing but a paint brush and happily stumble across a complete &lt;em&gt;Velociraptor&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Deinonychus&lt;/em&gt;!) skeleton which just had to be cleaned out from the surrounding layers of dust. This scenario would certainly make palaeontology way more straightforward and easy but it would also mean that excavations would be just boring routines where a hoover would do a better job than a naively enthusiastic undergrad student!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though excavation techniques are at least as numerous as excavation sites, the paint brush must be one of the rarest tools. Personally, I’ve tried things like hammering a cliff with a pike, shoveling dust and blocks of stone, digging in solid clay with an oyster knife or sifting tons of bags of sediments after diluting it in acid in a lab. None of these activities are similar to the restful act of flicking away sand with a brush (but they’re still a lot of fun!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Palaeontology is not dusty&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two points above are understandably confusing for the general public because of the Hollywood image of palaeontologists, depicted as &amp;quot;adventurers, not really serious, but entertaining&amp;quot; (to translate a quote from Eric Buffetaut’s book &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.editions-belin.com/ewb_pages/f/fiche-article-quoi-servent-les-dinosaures-22046.php&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;À quoi servent les dinosaures?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;). One might think that other scientists would have a better understanding of palaeontology. However, even if they generally understand the discipline and its implications better than the general public: &amp;quot;Paleontology has a reputation as a dry and dusty discipline, stymied by privileged access to fossil specimens that are interpreted with an eye of faith and used to evidence just-so stories of adaptive evolution&amp;quot; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0169534714000871&quot;&gt;Cunningham et al 2014&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, however, the discipline that studies traces of evolution has not escaped evolution of its own. The &amp;quot;privileged access to fossil specimens&amp;quot; has been replaced by either huge online databases (just &lt;a href=&quot;http://africanfossils.org/&quot;&gt;one example&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.morphobank.org/&quot;&gt;one other&lt;/a&gt; among thousands) or accessible and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/04/17/hide-and-seek-with-a-t-rex-in-a-drawer/&quot;&gt;well-curated collections&lt;/a&gt;. The &amp;quot;eye of faith&amp;quot; has been replaced by &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computed_tomography&quot;&gt;X-Ray tomography&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/06/14/an-army-of-skeletons-with-lasers/&quot;&gt;Surface scanners&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synchrotron&quot;&gt;synchrotrons&lt;/a&gt;; and the &amp;quot;just-so stories&amp;quot; are now replaced by integrative studies leading to a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0960982213009160&quot;&gt;new vision of the history of life&lt;/a&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Palaeontology is... great&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The differences between a nerdy &amp;quot;Indianajonesomorph&amp;quot; oryctologist that knows all of the dinosaurs’ names by heart and a realistic palaeontologist are what makes palaeontology so interesting. More than the taxonomy, taphonomy, comparative anatomy and cladistic tools that palaeontologists use, palaeontology is about the idea that everything is constantly changing and that we live in just one fleeting moment in the vast history of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I still like the image of the &amp;quot;adventurers, not really serious, but entertaining&amp;quot;... As long as palaeontologists don’t take this image seriously themselves!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: wikimedia commons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/06/09/what-isnt-palaeontology-like/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/What-isnt-palaeontology/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/What-isnt-palaeontology/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Easter bunny’s origins are linked with climate change</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Easterbunny_2-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot;&gt;
The Easter Bunny apparently originated in German Lutherans’ traditions before 1682 when it was first mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Georg_Franck_von_Franckenau&quot;&gt;von Franckenau’s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;De ovis paschalibus&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In France and Belgium however, it’s not a rabbit that hides eggs in the garden for Easter morning but flying bells coming back from Rome (they went there for their holidays since the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maundy_Thursday&quot;&gt;Maundy Thursday&lt;/a&gt;). For many people this makes no sense at all (flying bells, come on!) but on the other hand I think that a bunny carrying coloured eggs and hiding them does not make much more sense...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the Easter bunny makes a bit more sense than the bells after re-reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0059668&quot;&gt;Ge et al.’s&lt;/a&gt; excellent paper, on the evolution of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rabbits&quot;&gt;rabbits&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hares&quot;&gt;hares&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pikas&quot;&gt;pikas&lt;/a&gt; (careful: cuteness overload!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lagomorphs originated in the early Eocene in Asia (that’s around 55-50 Mya – million years ago), they then split during the mid-late Eocene (~40 Mya) into the two families we know today, the Orchotonidae (the pikas and 31 other genera) and the Leporidae (hares and rabbits, 45 genera). As you might have noticed from my former posts, I’m &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/03/29/dinosaurs-are-useless-if-they-dont-go-in-trees/&quot;&gt;vaguely&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/02/18/palaeo-poetry-and-placental-mammals/&quot;&gt;vaguely&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/10/18/the-placental-mammal-saga-special-summer-double-episode/&quot;&gt;vaguely&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/01/13/a-brave-new-world-of-monkeying-around-with-trees/&quot;&gt;vaguely&lt;/a&gt;) interested in integrating fossils and living species within phylogenies, well Ge et al’s paper is a really good example of why one should not ignore past diversity. If you only look at living Orchotonids, you would miss the 31 other genera (97% of the family’s generic diversity!). Furthermore, if you only look at the body mass variation in living species of Leporids you would miss the rabbit &lt;em&gt;T.rex&lt;/em&gt;:  &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuralagus_rex&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nuralagus&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;rex&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now let us go back to our question and see when did the Easter bunny really originate and what are the origins of its family’s diversity. During the late Eocene/early Oligocene (~35-31 Mya), the climate was warmer, wetter and had higher CO2 levels than nowadays. This climate corresponded with a landscape dominated by forest and an increased distribution of C3 &amp;quot;grasses&amp;quot; notably &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asteraceae&quot;&gt;Asteraceae&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rosaceae&quot;&gt;Rosaceae&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fabaceae&quot;&gt;Fabaceae&lt;/a&gt; which happens to be the principal diet of Orchotonids leading to an increased diversification in this group. However, Leporids, which appeared roughly during the same period, remained less diversified than their cute cousins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The climate became gradually colder and drier during the Oligocene and Miocene period to reach a global cold and dry climate during the late Miocene (~5-10 Mya) slightly after &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/16553316&quot;&gt;Nature’s Green Revolution&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; leading to the expansion of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/C4_carbon_fixation&quot;&gt;C4&lt;/a&gt; &amp;quot;grasses&amp;quot; namely the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poaceae&quot;&gt;poaceae&lt;/a&gt; (the true grasses). During this period, the number of Ochotonid genera &amp;quot;dramatically decreased&amp;quot; (to quote the authors) however Leporids expanded in both geographic range and generic diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the authors, it was this &amp;quot;Nature’s Green Revolution&amp;quot; and the rise of the C4 plants that drove the shift in dominance between the two families of Lagomorphs, allowing the Leporids, that could digest C4 plants successfully and therefore benefit more from the increasingly open landscapes to radiate during the Pliocene (~5 Mya).  Hopping may look ridiculous but it is actually a &lt;a href=&quot;http://stripe.colorado.edu/%7Ekram/kangaroo.pdf&quot;&gt;really efficient&lt;/a&gt; way to move around in open grasslands. This pattern of adaptation to global cooling and the rise of C4 plants is also found in the evolution of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bovidae&quot;&gt;Bovidae&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Equidae&quot;&gt;Equidae&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Ge et al.’s study gives us an explanation for why it is an Easter bunny that hides the eggs in C4 grass and not an Easter pika (hiding it in C3 grass). However, it is important to stress that these findings don’t in any way detract from flying bells or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jcjRAbj0ycE&quot;&gt;why we colour eggs&lt;/a&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: wikimedia commons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/04/18/the-easter-bunnys-origins-are-linked-with-climate-change-2/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/The-Easter-Bunny/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/The-Easter-Bunny/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hopsolete Trees</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Beer_bottles-300x205.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot;&gt;
One of the most unusual benefits of being in Ireland from a Southern French PhD student’s perspective is not so much the rain and the pronounced taste for culinary oddities (&lt;a href=&quot;http://j8.ly/popular-irish-chinese-dish-3-in-1-fried-rice&quot;&gt;some weird&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breakfast_roll&quot;&gt;some excellent&lt;/a&gt;) but the awesome trend towards a new age of craft beers (and I’m not mentioning the pillar of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guinness&quot;&gt;Irish pub culture&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the increasing beer richness available in any decent pub/off-licence, I was inspired to combine two of my passions: beer-related stuff and phylogeny-related stuff. Despite an honourable attempt by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jasonleebrown.org/jasonleebrown.org/beerlogeny.html&quot;&gt;J.L. Brown&lt;/a&gt;, I would like to discuss the three reasons why it’s imphopsible to build a true beer phylogeny. Admittedly one of the main reasons for this impossibility is the side effect of drinking any sugar rich (at least originally) drink that has been infected by &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saccharomyces_cerevisiae&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Saccharomyces cerevisiae&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;... But there are also three more theoretical reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To build phylogenies, you need data.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the fact that the data collection part of such a study could be great (doing your fieldwork in a pub, isn’t that cool?), I doubt the data base would actually be big enough to infer any well supported phylogenetic trees. Think about a matrix with only one character (let’s say presence or absence of bones) and with 4 species (a fly, a tuna, a pigeon and a walrus); you won’t be able to resolve the tree past the first node. Theoretically one needs at least a number of characters equal to the number of taxa (- 2 because you can cheat by ignoring the first and the last node).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s see what our data matrix looks like for beers: there are approximately &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beer_style&quot;&gt;180 different beer styles&lt;/a&gt; out there so we need at least 178 characters to classify them. Even if some characters come readily to your mind (ABV – alcool! –, colour, ingredients, taste), I’ll bet you cannot find more than 10 of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To build phylogenies, you need models.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When building a phylogeny, it is important to remember that the true questions we are asking our software are something like: (1) which tree involves the minimum number of changes or (2) which is the most likely tree regarding my data?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first question is the cladistics approach; using an optimal criterion parameter (usually parsimony) when you’re building your tree. It states that the best tree will be the one implying the least number of changes for grouping the tips together. The second question is the probabilistic approach, which is based on fitting a model of character evolution that will be the best fit for the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to our brews, the question we want to ask the software will mainly depend on the assumptions we have. A cladistic approach such as the one that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jasonleebrown.org/jasonleebrown.org/beerlogeny.html&quot;&gt;Brown&lt;/a&gt; used works as long as we have sampled enough characters back in the pub. However, unless each clade of beers has a clear pattern (e.g. only the stouts have an ABV between 4.5° and 5°) we are likely to suffer from the well-known &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Long_branch_attraction&quot;&gt;Long Branch Attraction&lt;/a&gt; artifact in some parts of the tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So can we use the probabilistic method instead? Again, as long as we have enough data, this method is possible but will it give an accurate result? Well, that depends on your model of character evolution. Since we cannot use the classic &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Models_of_DNA_evolution&quot;&gt;DNA evolution models&lt;/a&gt;, we will have to build our own evolutionary model implying that we have a reasonably guessable probability of going from one state to another for any character (e.g. the probability of moving along the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_Reference_Method&quot;&gt;Standard Reference Method&lt;/a&gt; color scale).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, Spencer and Wilberg (&lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cla.12018/full&quot;&gt;Cladistics – 2013&lt;/a&gt;) tested the actual evolutionary meaning of the two methods (although, they were fairly biased in favour of one of the two approaches).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To build phylogenies, you need... evolution.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A last point to this whole problem is that trying to reconstruct a realistic scenario of a clade’s evolution (i.e. a phylogeny) implies that the mechanism underlying the whole process is mainly descent with modification (but this is not exclusively necessary e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolutionary_linguistics&quot;&gt;evolutionary linguistics&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Horizontal_gene_transfer&quot;&gt;horizontal transfer&lt;/a&gt; – see my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/01/11/hey-tree-of-life-hows-it-growing/&quot;&gt;previous blog post&lt;/a&gt; or some more serious (awesome) views &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnas.org/content/96/7/3801&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v431/n7005/full/nature02848.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://mbe.oxfordjournals.org/content/29/6/1545&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding these three points, I must reluctantly abandon the idea of doing any proper beer phylogeny since it seems that a beer-types classification would look more like a massive network than a straightforward textbook example of a phylogenetic tree... To end with a more positive and less phylo-nerd point, these messy relationships between each type of beer allow us to enjoy creative, new craft beers such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galway_Hooker_%28beer%29&quot;&gt;Irish Pale Ales&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porterhouse_Brewery&quot;&gt;Oyster Stouts&lt;/a&gt; which are more than the sum of every element composing their name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for those that just don’t care, I’ll leave you with this excellent &lt;a href=&quot;http://aleheads.com/2010/11/30/in-defense-of-beer-styles/&quot;&gt;post by Barley McHops&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://aleheads.com/2010/11/30/in-defense-of-beer-styles/&quot;&gt;aleheads&lt;/a&gt; blog while I’m going to continue my sampling... Just in case...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: wikimedia commons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/04/11/hopsolete-trees/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Hopsolete-trees/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Hopsolete-trees/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gould Mine</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Gould-239x300.png&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot;&gt;
The career of Stephen Jay Gould eludes easy definition because of his prolific output in so many areas. &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Shermer&quot;&gt;Michael Shermer&lt;/a&gt; characterises him as a historian of science and scientific historian, popular scientist and scientific populariser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The popular science writings of Stephen Jay Gould (20 of his 22 books and hundreds of articles) are responsible for making me want to study macroevolution. He said of his popular essays that they were intended &amp;quot;for professionals and lay readers alike&amp;quot;. We have already covered some aspects of science communication, like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/02/10/the-heat-and-light-of-science-communication/&quot;&gt;how to do&lt;/a&gt; it and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/02/16/3d-dinosaurs-are-bringing-down-the-ivory-tower/&quot;&gt;which kind of scientists&lt;/a&gt; should engage in it. Gould wrote 479 academic papers during his career, so any thought of public outreach damaging one’s science certainly didn’t apply to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s have a closer look at his academic legacy. Gould is well known for his theory of &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Punctuated_equilibrium&quot;&gt;punctuated equilibrium&lt;/a&gt; co-written with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nileseldredge.com/&quot;&gt;Niles Eldredge&lt;/a&gt;. This fuelled the debate around ideas such as species selection and the mechanisms explaining macroevolutionary patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite this being the work for which he is best remembered it represents a tiny fraction of his output. He actually published only 15 papers with this theory as a main topic, which represents only 3% of his academic work! As a comparison, he published more papers (17) on baseball!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His primary field was invertebrate palaeontology (he was the curator of Harvard’s Invertebrate palaeontology collections from 1973 to his death in 2002) but again, even his main focus in this area (on Cerion snails) represents only on one quarter of his work. Shermer describes him as being &amp;quot;no single-minded fossil digger or armchair theorizer.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, nearly one fifth of his massive scientific output is primarily focused on the history of science. Again, as Shermer says, he was a &amp;quot;Historian of Science and Scientific historian&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Gould should not be only remembered for his proposal of punctuated equilibrium. Gould published 169 papers in 23 last years of last century, which gives him an average number of publications in the history of science of 7.34 per year. To put it in the historical context of the field, the only names that have been more productive are Aristotle, Kant, Goethe and Newton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s rare to see a scientist who divided opinion so much, hagiographies have been written about him but he’s also loathed. Look at these for contrasting views:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;In the field of evolutionary biology at large, Gould’s reputation is mud.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Steve is extremely bright, inventive. He thoroughly understands paleontology; he thoroughly understands evolutionary biology.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave it to the reader to find out where they stand on Gould for there is a lot of controversy to consume. I prefer to remember him through his essays on Natural History than through his few papers about punctuated equilibrium, better illustrating the &amp;quot;measure of a man&amp;quot; (that’s Shermer’s pun). His life illustrates how interdisciplinary studies exponentially increase scientific productivity: &amp;quot;Gould has used the history of science to reinforce his evolutionary theory (and vice versa)&amp;quot; writes Shermer. And that applies as much to punctuated equilibrium as to baseball!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: wikimedia commons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/02/28/gould-mine/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Gould-mine/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Gould-mine/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>3D dinosaurs are bringing down the Ivory Tower</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Pasta-Brontosaurus-300x196.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot;&gt;
Adam raised the point of science communication in his &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/02/10/the-heat-and-light-of-science-communication/&quot;&gt;last blog post&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; science should be communicated to a mainly interested and receptive public. The main question when thinking about science communication is &amp;quot;how should we do it?&amp;quot; However a second question, arising from this one would be &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;who&lt;/strong&gt; should do it?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe having an interest in popular science is the first step for starting a career as a scientist. Personally, I was influenced by &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jurassic_Park_%28film%29&quot;&gt;Jurassic Park&lt;/a&gt;, which gave me the idea that in a distant future I would (could) become a paleontologist. I believe this influence is shared by a vast majority of young paleontologists of this &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Dinosaur_Heresies&quot;&gt;Bakker dinosaur’s revolution&lt;/a&gt; generation. So, to me, even if Jurassic Park bent some scientific rules (the most obvious one being bringing stones to life), the film created a renewed interest in its related field of palaeontology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so that’s a good reason for popularizing science then? It’s not that easy. A fairly large amount of scientists will always look at such attempts to popularize science as a &amp;quot;bastard&amp;quot; child of the scientific adventure, a kind of side effect that makes scientists, in the best case, smile ironically. In the worst case though, they think it propagates massively erroneous ideas: like the one I pointed out above or -another that &amp;quot;makes me smile ironically&amp;quot; – that paleontologists are Indiana Jones-style adventurers that wander around the world and from time to time brush the sand and discover how velociraptors (read Deinonychus) were talking to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Whiteley&quot;&gt;Richard Whitley&lt;/a&gt; in his book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://link.springer.com/book/10.1007/978-94-009-5239-3&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Expository Science: Forms and Functions of Popularisation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, summarises the idea by writing that: &amp;quot;popularization is not viewed as part of the knowledge production and validation process but as something external to top research which can be left to non-scientists, failed scientists or ex-scientists as part of the general public relations effort of the research enterprise.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This vision of popularizing science is linked to the idea that an increased output of popular science leads to a fatal decrease of legitimate and accurate scientific progress. This is known as the ‘Sagan Effect’ after &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Sagan&quot;&gt;Carl Sagan&lt;/a&gt; and the erroneous claim that his legitimate scientific output decreased after the initiation of his popular science TV series: &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmos:_A_Personal_Voyage&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cosmos&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can one popularize science and actively do science?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one has a look at the actual numbers (scientific articles published vs. popular articles published), one expects that if popularizing science is reserved for &amp;quot;failed scientists&amp;quot;, people publishing more popular articles will publish fewer science articles. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/02/16/3d-dinosaurs-are-bringing-down-the-ivory-tower/en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michael_Shermer&quot;&gt;Michael Shermer&lt;/a&gt;, in his paper published in &lt;a href=&quot;http://sss.sagepub.com/content/32/4/489&quot;&gt;Social Studies of Science in 2002&lt;/a&gt;, brings down this popular belief by calculating the actual numbers of scientific papers published by these popular science writers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look at the numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a base line, while the four PIs publishing on this blog all take part in extra curricular activities, they are primarily research scientists. Last year, they published all together 22 papers which gives a respectable average of nearly one paper per PI published every two months! In contrast, if you look at the great popular science writers of the end of the last century (say Carl Sagan or Steven Jay Gould), during their massive and influential popularization of their fields, they produced an average of one paper per month for Sagan and nearly two papers a month for Gould (and that for 35 consecutive years!). So they seem to have it all: &amp;quot;legitimate&amp;quot; science output and successful careers as science communicators. Just looking at these figures, the myth of the trade-off between popular science writing and actual scientific production is just, as Shermer describes it, &amp;quot;a Chimera&amp;quot;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can one popularize science and actively do science?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes. And to go back to my first point, with Jurassic Park (which, in comparison to Gould or Sagans’ popular work can easily be classified as a &amp;quot;bad&amp;quot; way to do it), I believe that popularizing science is not a problem: in an altruistic world, scientists should focus on contributing to the advancement of their field by any means possible, not exclusively on their own amount of publications. Thankfully, most scientists manage to combine both popular communication and research output efficiently. I think that one important and still altruistic way to contribute to the advancement of a field is definitely science popularization. Richard Whitley says that &amp;quot;by successfully combining claims to universal validity and social utility through popularization, [Sagan and Gould] laid the foundation for the present domination and expansion of the sciences.&amp;quot; These contributions have a real long-term benefit to the advancement of the field. Firstly, the ideas of the authors of popular science become fixed in the public consciousness and secondly (most importantly to me), they inspire new generations of scientists that will, later on, personally contribute to the advancement of their field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this bad for &amp;quot;legitimate&amp;quot; scientific production? Not at all! By popularizing evolution in a realistic (or perhaps not so realistic) way, Gould and Jurassic Park spark the interest and imaginations of the next generation of potential scientist who, through their research, will make direct contributions to scientific research!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a positive feedback cycle: excellent scientists generate good science communicators; good scientific communication generates scientific interest and curiosity; scientific interest produces scientists and some of these scientists will go on to become good scientific communicators…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: wikimedia commons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/02/16/3d-dinosaurs-are-bringing-down-the-ivory-tower/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/3D-dinosaurs/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/3D-dinosaurs/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Levels of Selection</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Okasha-2006.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot;&gt;
Thanks to the magical (and sometimes frustrating!) technological capabilities of Google+, every fortnight we have international phylo/macro journal club meetings which span three continents and even include elements of time travel (the Australian participants are always in the future!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the varied &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/BetterOnTheMoon&quot;&gt;topics we cover&lt;/a&gt;, one of our recent sessions was a discussion of Samir Okasha’s book, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/Evolution-Levels-Selection-Samir-Okasha/dp/B005FOHQMG&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Evolution and Levels of Selection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Evolutionary biology is an empirical science which also receives attention from philosophers. The two approaches are often difficult to reconcile so Okasha’s book is a welcome bridge for the gap between philosophical theory and practical biology. We mainly focused on the chapter which deals with species selection, clade selection and macroevolution and addresses the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unit_of_selection&quot;&gt;units of selection&lt;/a&gt; debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a brief background, the debate hinges on the unit(s) and level(s) at which evolution by natural selection operates. Biological structures are inherently hierarchical. As researchers we tend to focus on specific organisational levels, so community ecologists will have very different concerns and interests to cell biochemists. Biological structures are shaped by evolution but the question is at which level(s) in the biological hierarchy does natural selection act? The theory of natural selection is an abstract concept; as &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Lewontin&quot;&gt;Lewontin&lt;/a&gt; describes, the tripartite conditions for evolution to occur are phenotypic variation, differential fitness and heritability. So which level of biological organisation satisfies these requirements? Well it seems like it depends on who you read and who influenced your evolution teachers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the UK and Ireland we are generally taught evolution from a gene-centric point of view – the Dawkins school of thinking in which selection acts at the level of the individual and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Selfish_Gene&quot;&gt;unit of selection is the gene&lt;/a&gt;, and only the gene. However, across the pond, there seem to be more proponents and acceptors of higher or multi-level selection theory; the idea (following &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steven_M._Stanley&quot;&gt;Stanley&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stephen_Jay_Gould&quot;&gt;Gould&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Niles_Eldredge&quot;&gt;Eldredge&lt;/a&gt; among others) that natural selection is not restricted to genes as the sole units of selection. It’s a confusing debate, especially when it comes to teasing apart the concepts of levels and units of selection; Okasha argues that a gene’s-eye view (genes as the units) can still be adopted for selection acting at various hierarchical levels. Furthermore, concepts of species level selection tend to become confused with &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Group_selection&quot;&gt;group selection&lt;/a&gt; – a notoriously controversial concept which is guaranteed to set alarm bells ringing for many people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Returning to Lewontin’s criteria, the basic idea of species level selection is simple. If species vary in some sort of traits and that variation gives rise to differential extinction or speciation rates, then some types of species will become more common than others. This approach is particularly common from palaeontological or macroevolutionary perspectives. If you’re interested in long-term evolutionary trends such as patterns of differential lineage abundances or extinction and speciation trends, it’s intuitive to treat the species as the level at which selection acts. This highlights a fundamental component of this debate: the gene-only-level of selection is usually advocated by microevolutionists; those who are interested in changes at the genetic level. In contrast, multilevel selection theory receives support from macroevolutionists who, due to their fundamentally different approaches, consider individual species to be their smallest units of interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you think about species selection it is often easy to confound it with clade selection yet Okasha draws a clear distinction between the two concepts. Clades are, by definition, monophyletic; comprised of a single ancestral species and all of its descendant species. Unlike species, clades cannot split to create new clades with ancestor-descendant relationships because any new clade will inevitably be nested within the old clade (the diagram in Okasha’s book makes all of this far clearer than my description!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Okasha2006-Fig7.1-300x224.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clade A is part of the larger clade B but it is not the offspring of clade B (offspring must have an independent existence from their parents and be able to outlive them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speciation and extinction rates are clearly not uniform; some lineages radiate into many different types of species which enjoy happy evolutionary lives (think of our arthropod-dominated world) while other evolutionary lineages produce fewer species. The question is whether these patterns are the result of species-level, macroevolutionary processes or whether emergent, species-level properties can be explained from selection acting at the genetic level. As an &amp;quot;acid test&amp;quot; for genuine species selection, Okasha proposes Elizabeth Vrba’s view that species selection must in principle (though not necessarily in practice) &amp;quot;be able to oppose selection at lower hierarchical levels&amp;quot;. Otherwise species level selection merely describes processes which can also be explained from a genetic-selection stance. For example, species selection may have been involved in the evolution or maintenance of sexual reproduction; the advantages of sexuality at the species level may have outweighed the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolution_of_sexual_reproduction#Two-fold_cost_of_sex&quot;&gt;two-fold cost of sex&lt;/a&gt; at the individual level and therefore favour the evolution of sexual over asexual lineages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there seems to be a general paucity of clear examples which conform to Vrba’s acid test. One intriguing suggestion as to why this may be the case is time. The generation times of species producing new lineages are clearly far longer than the generation times of individuals’ reproduction so perhaps comparatively sluggish species selection processes have not had sufficient time to oppose evolutionary patterns which arise from individual selection?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confused? It’s an interesting debate but certainly not one for the faint hearted and the fact that each philosopher/scientist/punter on the street seems to have jargon and slightly differing definitions of their own only serves to cloud the murky waters further. It is, however, interesting to contemplate how our own research backgrounds and the inclinations of our teachers influence our approach to the debate. If you’re interested in these kinds of questions then Okasha’s book is well worth the read or else you could join in with our Phylo/Macro journal club meeting; wherever you are in the world we’re on a Google+ hang out near you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: Okasha 2006, Evolution and the Levels of Selection&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/02/03/levels-of-selection/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt; co-written with Sive Finlay (sfinlay[at]tcd.ie, @SiveFinlay)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Levels-of-Selection/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Levels-of-Selection/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A brave new world of monkeying around with trees</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Tamarin_portrait_2_edit3-300x200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot;&gt;
I’ve spent the last few days writing an introduction for my first PhD paper on the practical issues of adding fossils to molecular phylogenies (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?feature=player_embedded&amp;amp;v=Y3ciaYSvbyU&quot;&gt;full recipe here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my starting point: most people working in macroevolution agree that we should &lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/mee3.2013.4.issue-8/issuetoc&quot;&gt;integrate fossils into modern phylogenetic trees&lt;/a&gt;. Of the many possible methods that are available, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sysbio.oxfordjournals.org/content/61/6/973.short&quot;&gt;Ronquist’s total evidence method&lt;/a&gt; looks to be the most promising (however, some &lt;a href=&quot;http://arxiv.org/abs/1310.2968&quot;&gt;nice other&lt;/a&gt; ones also exist).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently &lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/jeb.12237/abstract&quot;&gt;Schrago et al.&lt;/a&gt; published a nice attempt to use this method on the Plathyrrini (New-World monkeys to you and me):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/03/29/dinosaurs-are-useless-if-they-dont-go-in-trees/&quot;&gt;reminder&lt;/a&gt;, the aim of this total evidence method is to combine all of the available data: both molecular and morphological. Traditionally, analyses have treated each type of data separately; approaches which bring their own advantages and problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the molecules:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1055790305003817&quot;&gt;Opazo et al.&lt;/a&gt; published in 2006 a classical example of a molecular phylogenetics study. There are more recent, impressive phylogenetic studies (like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.plosgenetics.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001342&quot;&gt;Perelman et al.&lt;/a&gt; in 2011 and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.plosone.org/article/info:doi/10.1371/journal.pone.0049521&quot;&gt;Springer et al.&lt;/a&gt; in 2012) on most of the primates and using more genetic data but I think Opazo is a better example of a traditional approach because it involves a tree with 17 taxa instead of more than 200.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Opazo.et_.al2006-Fig5-264x300.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opazo et al. 2006 Fig. 5. A Platyrrhini dated phylogeny – values indicate the age of the nodes, the circle at the root of the tree is the fossil used for age calibration: Branisella.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two of the main advantages of this approach are the quantity of data involved (tens of thousands base pairs) and the methods of inferring the evolutionary history: molecular evolutionary models are easy to understand and easy to implement (each site has a finite number of states – A, C, G, T or nothing – and &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Models_of_DNA_evolution&quot;&gt;probabilistic models&lt;/a&gt; are good enough to infer the rate of changes from one state to the other). From a data perspective, another practical advantage is that, with modern &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DNA_sequencing#Next-generation_methods&quot;&gt;NextGen sequencing&lt;/a&gt;, it’s really easy and fast to obtain a full genomic dataset. However, the main inconvenience from a macroevolutionary point of view is that molecular approaches don’t really take evidence from the fossil record into account. In the Opazo example, the only fossil used is &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Branisella&quot;&gt;Branisella&lt;/a&gt;, and the only useful information here is just its age (around 26 Ma) used to calibrate the time on the tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S004724840700187X&quot;&gt;Kay et al.&lt;/a&gt; 2008 published an awesome study of the Platyrrhini history from a palaeontological point of view. They focused on 20 living taxa combined with 11 fossil species and using 268 morphological characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Kay.et_.al2008-Fig21-188x300.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kay et al. 2008 Fig. 21. A Platyrrhini phylogeny based on morphological data including fossils&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, there are both advantages and problems associated with this approach. Firstly, the number of characters used is pretty low; don’t get me wrong, 268 is really good for a morphological matrix, it’s just low compared to molecular data. Furthermore, the underlying evolutionary models used to build the phylogeny are hard to infer, the most common model is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://sysbio.oxfordjournals.org/content/50/6/913.short&quot;&gt;Lewis 2001 Mk model&lt;/a&gt; where morphological characters are treated as if they &amp;quot;act like&amp;quot; molecular sites with no assumptions made about their states or rates of change (this method has been &lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cla.12018/full&quot;&gt;criticized&lt;/a&gt; but it’s still our best way to infer morphological evolution). Another solution, which is also commonly used, is to infer nothing but instead just use a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maximum_parsimony_%28phylogenetics%29&quot;&gt;maximum parsimony approach&lt;/a&gt;: find the tree which explains observed phenotypic evolution with the fewest number of evolutionary steps (characters changing from one state to another on a particular node within the tree). However, compared to a purely molecular approach, the advantages of Kay’s tree are clear from a macroevolutionary point of view: this tree includes full information from the morphologies of both living and fossil species!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now hopefully you can see where I’m coming from in wanting to use the total evidence method? It’s clear from the empirical examples above that the problems associated with one approach are the advantages in the other. So let’s just combine them! And that’s what Schrago did in their work, they just mixed both data sets and re-ran the analysis (or, more precisely, they used Kay’s data set as it was but added new genomic data collected over the last seven years to Opazo’s data set). Here’s their result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Schrago.et_.al2006-Fig2-300x236.png&quot; alt=&quot;_config.yml&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kay et al. 2008 Fig. 21. A Platyrrhini phylogeny based on morphological data including fossils&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here we have the advantage of both methods combined and this tree is far more user friendly for macroevolutionary studies; one can test evolutionary hypothesis through time using a more complete representation of the Platyrrhini evolutionary history. One major problem still remains though; the paucity of useful morphological data compared to the wealth of molecular data which is now available. Does that influence the tree’s topology somehow? Well, stay tuned, my simulations are running...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: wikimedia commons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/01/13/a-brave-new-world-of-monkeying-around-with-trees/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/A-Brave-new-world/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/A-Brave-new-world/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How do Lego cars evolve?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/downloadE2979141711C7E66AA9DC037D0D66D3C-300x162.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot;&gt;
The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eseb2013.com/&quot;&gt;ESEB&lt;/a&gt; conference this August in Lisbon was not only about &lt;em&gt;Drosophila&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_Bock&quot;&gt;#superbock&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the useful discussions and the interesting talks, a definite highlight came from our very own &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tcd.ie/Zoology/research/research/theoretical/healy/healy.php&quot;&gt;Kilkenny scaling man&lt;/a&gt; all about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0003347213003060&quot;&gt;time perception and comparative analysis&lt;/a&gt;... Argh no I missed that one – apparently there was even a realistic &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiger_beetle&quot;&gt;Tiger Beetle&lt;/a&gt; hunting impression! There were at least eight overlapping talks at any one time and, as I had already seen Kevin’s talk, I went to listen to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bokmalab.net/&quot;&gt;Folmer Bokma&lt;/a&gt;’s insightful &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eseb2013.com/delegates/fbokma&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt Bokma’s talk was a good follow-up to Gene Hunt’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eseb2013.com/delegates/ghunt&quot;&gt;excellent talk&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Punctuated_equilibrium&quot;&gt;gradualism vs. stasis&lt;/a&gt; which he demonstrated through his careful study of the Ostracod fossil record, recently published in the excellent August issue of &lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/2041-210X.12085/abstract&quot;&gt;Methods in Ecology and Evolution&lt;/a&gt;. By means of a lengthy introduction with citation of more or less unknown people such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hugh_Falconer&quot;&gt;H. Falconer&lt;/a&gt; and C. Darwin, Bokma emphasised the fact that examples of evolutionary stasis are well known from the fossil record and that ideas of species undergoing rapid adaptations that were not specifically linked to environmental changes have been around since the 19th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bokma argued that trait co-adaptation is an important source of evolutionary changes. He cleverly illustrated this argument by means of a Lego car; I always think that using something other than just slides in a presentation greatly improves the talk! He argued that changes in colour or shape attributes can happen &amp;quot;easily&amp;quot; over a short evolutionary period as an adaptation to environmental changes. For example, characteristics of fur in &lt;em&gt;Vulpes &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Red_fox&quot;&gt;vulpes&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_fox&quot;&gt;lagopus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; foxes (the colour of the Lego car) or beak sizes in &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darwin_Finch&quot;&gt;Darwin’s finches&lt;/a&gt; (the windscreen of the Lego car) have evolved to increase the fitness of the individuals living in particular environmental conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But things get trickier when it comes to major changes or adaptations. Bokma illustrated this idea by trying to change the overall shape of the car (like going from a regular car to a truck). As soon as he started to remove one wheel, the car totally lost its fitness! For non-Lego fans he also gave the example of enzymatic reactions in endotherms: if just one enzyme evolves to be more active at a temperature different to normal body temperature, then there is no increase in fitness for the organism (and probably a decrease as that precise enzyme will be less efficient). It is only when all enzymes co-evolve to be more active at a different body temperature that there might be an increase of fitness for an individual. Bokma used this example to emphasise the irreversibility of evolution and how lineages can get stuck in &amp;quot;evolutionary dead-ends&amp;quot;. In response to H. Falconer’s comment to Darwin (1862) that the Elephant remains &amp;quot;unchangeable &amp;amp; unchanged&amp;quot;, Bokma argued that it might be &amp;quot;easy&amp;quot; (in an evolutionary way) to become an elephant but once you’re there, climbing into trees or crawling underground becomes tricky. So for these bigger evolutionary changes (the &amp;quot;jumps&amp;quot; in punctuated equilibrium theory), one needs a &amp;quot;genetic revolution&amp;quot;; evolving from a flightless theropod to a turkey involves co-adaptation of more than just locomotory characters. There is a strong irreversibility component to evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While some people were kind of miffed by Bokma’s talk and started a polite but energetic debate involving genetic mumbo jumbo, I just thought that his talk was a great illustration of the problem of stasis and jumps in evolution. As Gene Hunt demonstrated, evolutionary stasis and jumps are clearly dominant in the history of life but they are trickier to explain than gradualist evolution. However, to be objective I have to agree with some of the general comments on Bokma’s talk; &amp;quot;So what? We already knew that.&amp;quot; It reminded me of S.J. Gould’s excellent review on part of this idea in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Panda%27s_Thumb:_More_Reflections_in_Natural_History&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Panda’s Thumb&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (1980): The Return of the Hopeful Monster. So yes, we do already know about the ideas Bokma presented and he didn’t bring any staggering new insights but I believe he illustrated it with talent and brio! And perhaps I should mention that I can’t be completely objective here; I just love Lego, sorry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: Thomas Guillerme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/11/04/how-do-lego-cars-evolve/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Lego-cars/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Lego-cars/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Raptor-ous Reception</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/IMG_5224-300x200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot;&gt;
Thanks to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.trinitysocieties.ie/society/104/zoological-society&quot;&gt;DU ZooSoc&lt;/a&gt;, TCD staff and students were treated to an exhibition from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dublinfalconry.com/&quot;&gt;Dublin Falconry&lt;/a&gt; last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set against the busy backdrop of joggers and Pav-frequenters, six beautiful birds of prey were the stars of their own lunch time show. Here’s a few pictures from the event, just a flavour of the stunning animals which we were privileged to see, touch (and hear!) up close. And for the full effect, have a look at Keith McMahon’s beautiful &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AEbfH0wefbc&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/IMG_5224.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/IMG_5224.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bodyimg&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Whooo’s a pretty boy then? Barn Owl.&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/IMG_5285-215x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bodyimg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;Beautiful Scandinavian barn owl.&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/IMG_5250-237x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bodyimg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;Mmm, tasty finger.&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/IMG_5261-300x200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bodyimg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;Protective sleeve put to good work.&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/IMG_5217-210x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bodyimg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;Ready to take off... Peregrine falcon.&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/IMG_5372-300x188.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bodyimg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&amp;quot;I feel like chicken tonight...&amp;quot;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/IMG_5385-234x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bodyimg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;Juvenile Common buzzard – &amp;quot;If he looks like he’s coming towards you then duck!&amp;quot;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/IMG_5405-300x200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;bodyimg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;What paint brushes? Bengal eagle owl.&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: Thomas Guillerme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/10/25/a-raptor-ous-reception/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt; writen by Sive Finlay, sfinlay[at]tcd.ie, @SiveFinlay&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/A-raptorous-reception/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/A-raptorous-reception/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Placental mammal saga; special summer double episode</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Flickr_-_ggallice_-_Rodent-300x240.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot;&gt;
As I wrote in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/02/18/palaeo-poetry-and-placental-mammals/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; last winter, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stonybrook.edu/sb/images/features/oleary130208.pdf&quot;&gt;O’Leary et al.&lt;/a&gt; added their oar into the Placental Mammal origins debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone who missed that episode, they argued, with the backing of masses of morphological data, that placental mammal orders appeared right after the extinction of non-avian dinosaurs (also known as the explosive model). This was in opposition to two other views based on DNA data which argue that placentals appeared way before (long-fuse model) or slightly before (short-fuse model) the Mexican dinosaurs had to deal with some &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicxulub_crater&quot;&gt;meteorite&lt;/a&gt;... Again, have a look at this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/02/18/palaeo-poetry-and-placental-mammals/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; criticizing O’Leary et al.’s paper and how they &amp;quot;forgot&amp;quot; to use (ignored?) state-of-the-art phylogenetic inference methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was away feeding mosquitoes in Finland – and wondering whether the lack of fishes for dinner was due to my poor fishing skills or the absence of fishes in the river – Science published two new episodes of the placental saga. Of the two, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/341/6146/613.2.full&quot;&gt;Springer et al.&lt;/a&gt; took the decision to properly criticize the methods of O’Leary et al.’s work. Amongst their detailed methods review, they particularly underlined the inaccuracy of O’Leary et al.’s explosive model; such a hypothesis would imply that the early placental mammals had a rate of molecular change similar to that of retroviruses. For over ten years it has been widely accepted that molecular rates (i.e. the number of DNA changes that are transmitted to descendants) vary among lineages through time. Knowing that, one can estimate these rates (or call it speed if you’re more comfortable with that) of evolution by calibrating phylogenetic trees with fossils. So, in this case, the amount of evolution needed to evolve from the late Cretaceous (~65 myr) non-placental mammals to the first placental mammals (~58 myr) has to be as high as evolutionary rates more characteristic of retroviruses to realistically explain this evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Herein lies the eternal debate between palaeontologists and molecular biologists. The former base their estimations on the morphological changes they can see in the fossil record (even though some, as O’Leary et al. also include molecular data) while the latter calculate their evolutionary rate estimations on the molecular changes that they infer from living species’ DNA. Fundamentally, each method is valid but they are describing slightly different things ; palaeontologists infer the rates of changes between morphospecies (i.e. species that are separated based on their morphology) while molecular biologists study the rates of changes between surviving genetic pools (i.e. the populations leading to living species). My guess is that the true evolutionary history (i.e. the morphological and molecular changes of all the populations –fossils and living– through time) is to be found somewhere between these two approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s what I think O’Leary et al. demonstrated in their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/341/6146/613.3.full&quot;&gt;response to Springer et al.’s comments&lt;/a&gt;. Through a kind of a dodgy answer in reply to the technical points that Springer et al. underlined as the “retrovirusesomorph” rates, O’Leary’s team reran the analysis and found that yes, maybe the explosive model is not very realistic regarding the molecular data but neither is the long-fuse model regarding the palaeontological data. So which one should we choose? Hmmm, why not just go for the middle way with the short-fuse model? OK let’s do that – without calling it a short-fuse model though (they called it an “explosive model” in figure 2-B but to my mind at least, it’s getting closer to the short-fuse one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So all that for what? Nobody can either deny O’Leary et al.’s amazing work nor claim that the long-fuse model is realistic; the consensual short-fuse model remains pretty well supported among both moderate palaeontologists and molecular biologists. However, I still cherish this paper because it shows how I think good science should always work; find the two extreme scenarios and then study the median one…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: Wikimedia commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/10/18/the-placental-mammal-saga-special-summer-double-episode/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/The-placental-mammal-saga/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/The-placental-mammal-saga/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>