<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blog backup</title>
    <description>Backup blog posts from various blogs.</description>
    <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io</link>
    <atom:link href="http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Formally informal conferences</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-04-04-14.10.45.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot; /&gt; &lt;!-- Use one of the images --&gt;
One of my favourite part of working as a researcher during the summer (aside from quiet campuses with less students around) definitely has to be the “conference season”.
Indeed, I don’t need to convince many people that conferences are one of the lively and exciting part of doing science that rightly mix travelling, networking (and sometimes drinking) and learning about so many new things (and sometimes hangovers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the problems though is that they can sometimes be overwhelming.
It’s hard to find a balance between the right amount of networking (how many friends/collaborators do I want to meet and how many new ones do I want to make) and the right amount of learning (which talk do I want to attend and how much can I get from them).
Although everyone has its own technique to deal with these questions, it seems to me that it boils down to the number of people attending the conference and the objectives of the conference organisers.
I.e. one solution is to aim conferences towards a more human size with a clear emphasis on networking and learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And well, one such conference is the annual &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.britishecologicalsociety.org/membership-community/special-interest-groups/macroecology/&quot;&gt;BES Macro&lt;/a&gt; conference!
As has became a happy ritual over the last 4 years, I was awaiting July with impatience for this year’s one organised in Oxford by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nhcooper123&quot;&gt;Natalie Cooper&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rich_&quot;&gt;Rich Grenyer&lt;/a&gt;.
As a disclaimer though, I do not consider myself as a macro&lt;em&gt;ecologist&lt;/em&gt; at all (most of my work is on macro&lt;em&gt;evolution&lt;/em&gt; methods).
So why so I go every year? I don’t even know &lt;a href=&quot;http://rsbl.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/8/6/904&quot;&gt;what macroecology is&lt;/a&gt;!
Well one of the first point is that this conference covered a vast array of topics, this year reaching far beyond the classic bird species richness heat maps with presentations on microbes populations in tree holes or sampling biases in the fossil record!
The second point is because I think this conference ticks all the points that I think makes a good conference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-mix-different-career-levels&quot;&gt;First, mix different career levels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For early career scientists as myself it can sometimes be a bit intimidating to mainly hear these talks by “veteran” scientists.
In fact I often think to myself just before giving a talk, how lame mine will be in comparison to the other people.
Not that mixing different career levels makes my talk less lame, it has at least the benefit of making me feel better.
It also has the undeniable benefit of making it easier to network with the big wigs if you spoke in the same session as them.
At BES Macro conference, each session was a right mix between every career levels making it much more casual.
Even for the plenary speakers that ranged from Professor &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TimBlackburn66&quot;&gt;Tim Blackburn&lt;/a&gt; to About-to-be-doctor &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hannah_wht&quot;&gt;Hannah White&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;second-make-most-of-the-talks-short&quot;&gt;Second, make most of the talks short&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People have mixed feelings about lightning talks: from the speakers point of view, when you have exciting results it can be frustrating to convey your message in 5 minutes.
Also these talks are sometimes more difficult to write than a classic 10-15 minutes one!
However, from a listener’s point of view, think about how much more do you absorb, on average, from these extra 5-10 minutes that make a classic talk?
On a couple of talks: probably much more; on 2 days or more of conference: probably not much more!
Besides, if 5 minutes was not enough and just teased your curiosity, it makes an excellent opportunity to network (“Hi, I really enjoyed your talk. About that, [insert your burning question here]?”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;third-add-a-nice-dose-of-transferable-skills&quot;&gt;Third, add a nice dose of transferable skills&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another point of conferences that can be negative is that you chain-listen to many many talks all day long.
That has the benefit of giving a good overview of your field of research but can also make you slightly sleepy!
One solution to break this continuous rhythm of talks is to do it with discussion sessions that can either be about transferable skills or about big questions in the field.
For example, at the BES Macro conference we had an excellent discussion session on &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;reproducibility&lt;/a&gt; &lt;!-- add Leila&#39;s post here? --&gt;
or the classic “what is Macroecology?” question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;and-finally-dont-forget-to-add-some-rants&quot;&gt;And finally, don’t forget to add some rants&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes a good conference lies also in how much do you feel part of the field of research covered by the conference.
One way to convey that is to be part or at least listen to the “hot” debates shaking the field.
In this conference for example, we had two “official rants” by &lt;a href=&quot;http://shaimeirilab.weebly.com/&quot;&gt;Shai Meiri&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/acalgar&quot;&gt;Adam Algar&lt;/a&gt; on what is going wrong in macroecology (but still how much cool work is done).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, the main ingredient is the attitude of the people towards the conference.
As &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rich_&quot;&gt;Rich Grenyer&lt;/a&gt; put it in his welcoming introduction: &lt;em&gt;“this conference is formally informal.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope to see you at the next conference!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: Thomas Guillerme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/BESMacro/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/BESMacro/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>3 years as a PhD student</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/2015-04-04-14.10.45.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot; /&gt;
I arrived in Ireland October 2012 with the purpose of undertaking a PhD supervised by &lt;a href=&quot;http://nhcooper123.github.io/&quot;&gt;Natalie Cooper&lt;/a&gt;  on Primates evolution. Looking back, the start of the whole endeavour seemed really stressful to me (new country, new customs, new language) and the project just as frightening (&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepalaeoscene.wordpress.com/2015/10/01/what-do-you-actually-do-in-your-first-week-of-your-phd/&quot;&gt;what do I do?&lt;/a&gt;, where do I start?, will I be able to do it?)… What happened after was way &lt;strong&gt;below&lt;/strong&gt; my expectations: these three years were anything but stressful and frightening!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, even though not everything went smoothly and it had to take the best of the personalities (that are thankfully common sights in Trinity College’s Zoology Department) for dealing with some ups and downs, here is my top 5 list of personal thoughts that always improved the two aspects of my PhD: the working aspect (the research) and the “social” aspect (feeling relaxed and enjoying it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;be-ready-to-change-your-phd&quot;&gt;Be ready to change your PhD&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in the first line, my PhD was supposed to be on Primates evolution. In t&lt;a href=&quot;http://figshare.com/articles/Macroevolution_with_living_and_fossil_species/1583337&quot;&gt;the end&lt;/a&gt;, the world “Primates” is mentioned only once (and that is, buried in a sentence about several other mammalian orders). Of course, sometimes the PhD is a Long Quiet River if everything goes well and you keep your highest interest in the original topic. However, sometimes it changes completely! And this should never be a problem! The PhD should be allowed to evolve just as much as yourself (or more pragmatically: your field) evolves into these three or four years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;failure-happens-to-everyone&quot;&gt;Failure happens to everyone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another major part about the PhD (and about the scientific endeavour itself!) is that it will fail. More or less often and more or less dramatically in each case but failure should just be part of the process. As a early career researcher, you can learn a lot from the mistakes and the success of others. However, I found that there is nothing much more personally instructing than the trial and error. I already mentioned how my &lt;a href=&quot;www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/10/06/phd-pretty-huge-disaster/&quot;&gt;biggest PhD disaster&lt;/a&gt; led to my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/10/13/phd-positive-happy-developments/&quot;&gt;most positive development&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stay-open-minded-and-curious&quot;&gt;Stay open minded and curious&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing the thesis or even just doing the lab/computer work for the PhD can narrow your mind and highly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/05/10/surviving-experiments/&quot;&gt;decrease your sanity&lt;/a&gt;. I found that the best way to avoid that was to try as much as possible to make the PhD only priority number two and put all the other things (seminars, meeting speakers, chatting/helping colleagues, etc…) before it. It has two advantages for the PhD: (1) you don’t work on it 24/7 and (2) everything you learn outside of it will actually be super useful for the PhD. In the Zoology Department, we were only a couple of people doing macroevolution surrounded by ecologists. Yet, I think my work benefited heavily from the influence from these people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-rush&quot;&gt;Don’t rush&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I found nice with the PhD is that before you even start – before day one! – you already know the final deadline. OK, at day one, the handing in date seems far away (3 or 4 years away actually!) but that leaves you plenty of time for doing awesome research, writing it down as papers/chapters (and even trying to publish them before the deadline) and going to the pub or to other non-PhD recreational events…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chat-with-your-colleagues&quot;&gt;Chat with your colleagues&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I found that I gained so much just by chatting with my colleagues. And by colleagues I mean my fellow PhD students of course but also with the post-docs and the staff. I always found a long term benefit to both PhD aspects, whether it was talking about the latests video games during working time (I’m not only looking at you &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/yodacomplex&quot;&gt;@yodacomplex&lt;/a&gt;) or having heated debates about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/?s=species+selection&quot;&gt;species selection&lt;/a&gt; during coffee time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know much of these tips worked for me but might not apply to other people. In the end their is only one ultimate tip: make your PhD a hell of a good time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: Thomas Guillerme&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2015/11/19/3-years-as-a-phd-student/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 19 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/3YearsAsAPhD/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/3YearsAsAPhD/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Skeleton in the Closet</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/IMG_1618.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot; /&gt;
After a few &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/10/13/phd-positive-happy-developments/&quot;&gt;ups&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/10/06/phd-pretty-huge-disaster/&quot;&gt;downs&lt;/a&gt;, everything you always wanted to know about the effect of missing data on recovering topology using a Total Evidence approach is now &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1055790315002547&quot;&gt;available online (Open Access)&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper also treats many different questions that people might be interested in (Bayesian vs. ML; how to compare tree topologies; comparing entire distributions, not only their means and variance; and many more!) but I’ll leave it to you to discover it…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back on track, more than one an a half CPU centuries of calculation ago, &lt;a href=&quot;http://nhcooper123.github.io/&quot;&gt;Natalie&lt;/a&gt; and myself wanted to build a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/03/29/dinosaurs-are-useless-if-they-dont-go-in-trees/&quot;&gt;Total Evidence tip-dated primates tree&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;strong&gt;Total Evidence method&lt;/strong&gt; is the method that allows you to combine both living and fossil species (or actually, read “both molecular and morphological data”’’”) into the same phylogenies. The &lt;strong&gt;tip-dating method&lt;/strong&gt;, is an additional method that uses the age of the tips rather than the age of the nodes for dating such a tree. But I’m not going to talk about that in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start of the project, we were both confident about the idea behind it and that primates would be the ideal group for such work since they are so well studied. A study that I described in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/01/13/a-brave-new-world-of-monkeying-around-with-trees/&quot;&gt;former post&lt;/a&gt; also came out around the same time, encouraging us and comforting us in this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as you might guess, something went wrong, horribly wrong! For the Total Evidence method, we need molecular data for living species (&lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0049521&quot;&gt;check&lt;/a&gt;) morphological data for fossils species (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v498/n7452/full/nature12200.html&quot;&gt;check&lt;/a&gt;) and also for living species (che… No, wait)! After looking at the available data, we quickly found out that there was a crucial lack of living taxa with available morphological data (check our preprint to be submitted to Biology Letters putting the actual numbers on the problem). From that problem, rose the idea of actually testing how that would influence our analysis. And funnily enough, this problem become one of the two major parts of my PhD!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running thorough (and loooooong) simulations, we assessed the impact of missing data on topology when using a Total Evidence method. We looked at three parameters where data would be missing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The first one, was obviously the one I introduced above: the &lt;strong&gt;number of living taxa with no available morphological data&lt;/strong&gt; (at all!).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The second one, was the &lt;strong&gt;amount of available data in the fossil record&lt;/strong&gt; (because yes, fossils can be a bit patchy).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;And the third one, the &lt;strong&gt;overall amount of morphological characters&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then compared the effect of different levels of available data for each parameter individually and and their combination on recovering the correct topology, using both Maximum Likelihood and Bayesian Inference. For the correct topology, we used the tree that had no missing data in our simulations. For each parameter combination, we measured the clades in common between the correct topology and the trees with missing data as well as the placement of wild-card taxa (typically fossils jumping everywhere).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, we found that the number of living taxa with no available morphological data was the most important parameter for recovering a good topology. In fact, once you go past 50% living taxa with no morphological data, the two other parameters have no effect at all, even if you have a perfect or a really bad fossil record or many or really few characters. This is kind of intuitive when you think about it because the only way to branch the fossils to living taxa is to use the morphological data. Therefore, if there are no morphological data for the living taxa, the fossils cannot branch with them regardless of the quality of the data. Therefore, in this paper, we argue that to improve our topologies in Total Evidence, we should visit more Natural History museums. And not only the exciting fossil collections but the well curated collections of living species as well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the code for this paper is available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/TGuillerme/Total_Evidence_Method-Missing_data&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slideshare.net/ThomasGuillerme/total-evidence-phylogenies-the-missing-data-issue&quot;&gt;latest presentation&lt;/a&gt; about both papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paper 1&lt;/strong&gt;: Guillerme &amp;amp; Cooper 2015 – E&lt;em&gt;ffects of missing data on topological inference using a Total Evidence approach&lt;/em&gt; – Molecular Phylogenetic and Evolution (&lt;a href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ympev.2015.08.023&quot;&gt;doi:10.1016/j.ympev.2015.08.023&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paper 2 (preprint)&lt;/strong&gt;:  Guillerme &amp;amp; Cooper 2015 – &lt;em&gt;Assessment of cladistic data availability for living mammals&lt;/em&gt; – bioRxiv (&lt;a href=&quot;http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2015/07/28/022970&quot;&gt;doi: http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/022970&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: Thomas Guillerme (AMNH collections)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2015/09/10/the-skeleton-in-the-closet/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Skeleton-in-the-Closet/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Skeleton-in-the-Closet/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Evolution is – surprise! – Darwinian!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/800px-Human_pidegree-257x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot; /&gt;
I sometime come across papers that I missed during their publication time and that shed a new light on my current research (or strengthen the already present light). Today it was &lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/evan.21324/abstract&quot;&gt;Cartmill’s 2012 Evolutionary Anthropology&lt;/a&gt; – not open access, apologies…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cartmill raises an interesting question from an evolutionary point of view: “How long ago did the first [&lt;em&gt;insert your favorite taxa here&lt;/em&gt;] live?”. This question is crucial for any macroevolutionary study (or/and for the sake of getting a chance to be published in Nature). If one is studying the “rise of the age of mammals” (just &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/10/29/say-the-rise-of-the-age-of-mammals-again-i-double-dare-you/&quot;&gt;for example&lt;/a&gt; of course) the question of the exact timing is crucial to see whether placental mammals evolved after or before the extinction of avian dinosaurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Cartmill published in &lt;em&gt;Evolutionary Anthropology&lt;/em&gt; let’s replace [&lt;em&gt;insert your favorite taxa here&lt;/em&gt;] with humans. He proposes to answer to the question “How long ago did the first humans live?” by looking at the different ways people have addressed it through time. It all starts back with Simpson’s quantum evolution stating that clades share “adaptive shifts” or “adaptive trends”. For example, for humans, that will be bipedalism and an increase in brain size: “Everybody can sort humans out instantly from other sorts of things: […] they share a unique reliance on technology, a capacity for culture, and a gift for gab.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an unfortunate classical view of evolution based on morphological data leading to a series of morphological discontinuities – the adaptive shifts (“human origins, primate origins, mammal origins, amniote origins, and so on” – I already discussed this gradualistic view about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2012/12/10/sex-on-the-beach/&quot;&gt;tetrapod origins&lt;/a&gt;). Cartmill uses a pertinent quote from Simpson to comment this trend: “Is this not, in fact, simply a recrudescence of the old naïve conception of a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Great_chain_of_being&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;scala naturae&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[?]”. However, this raises a cladistic problem. Assuming we have the data on the oldest human. What defines his or her humanness? “Humanness [whatever that means] is not a coherent package. We have known since the 1960s that our terrestrial bipedality evolved more than two million years before the onset of what was long held to be the fundamental human characteristic, that is the great development of the brain.’’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cartmill’s point is that, morphologically, there is no adaptive shift or trend that can define any group. Morphological evolution acts more like a succession of slow and discrete incremental changes rather than the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantum_evolution&quot;&gt;Simpsonian quantum model&lt;/a&gt;: “there is only a long, geologically slow cascade of accumulating small apomorphies” and adaptive trends or shifts within clades “are fantasies, born ultimately of our wish to see ourselves as more decisively set off from other animals than we actually are.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will I have to rethink my current project looking at mammals morphological evolution? Well by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/01/13/a-brave-new-world-of-monkeying-around-with-trees/&quot;&gt;using molecular data as well as morphological data&lt;/a&gt; we can accurately trace back the small incremental changes (the DNA mutations) as well as the actual changes in morphology through time. My PhD is not just a series of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/10/06/phd-pretty-huge-disaster/&quot;&gt;failures&lt;/a&gt; after all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: wikimedia commons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2015/03/27/evolution-is-surprise-darwinian/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Evolution-is-darwinian/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Evolution-is-darwinian/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Do you speak Yamnaya?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Pieter_Bruegel_the_Elder_-_The_Tower_of_Babel_Vienna_-_Google_Art_Project_-_edited-300x220.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot; /&gt;
I bet you do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One nice non-biological thing you can do with phylogenetics (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/04/11/hopsolete-trees/&quot;&gt;unlike beers&lt;/a&gt;) is study the evolution of languages. If you aren’t familiar with &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evolutionary_linguistics&quot;&gt;evolutionary linguistics&lt;/a&gt;, it’s basically the same principles that we use to study the descent with modification of organisms but applied to words. Even though words do not evolve in a biological way, we can still apply similar phylogenetic principles by just adjusting the evolutionary models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK but let’s go back to my assumption (that you do speak Yamnaya). Since you are reading this blog post that I’m trying to write in English, you do speak English which is part of the linguistic family (or clade) called the Indo-European that consists of the vast majority of the European and Indian languages spoken by a good 3 billion people (as the name originally suggests- check this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sssscomic.com/comic.php?page=196&quot;&gt;excellent visual phylogenetic summary&lt;/a&gt;). Even though it is not straightforward to see the similarities between Icelandic and Indi, evolutionary linguistics suggest that both languages have diverged from the same language based on words and grammar similarities. This language, generically called proto-Indo-European is estimated to have originated either around 9000 years ago in the Middle-East and spread across India and Europe along with agriculture (the “Anatolian hypothesis”). Or, a second theory postulates its origin around 5000 years ago on the northern shores of the Black Sea and its subsequent spread along with horse riding and wheeled transport (the “steppe hypothesis”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until last month, both hypotheses were lacking data to explain some crucial temporal problems: the proto-Indo-European language contains words related to wheeled vehicles which were not invented 9000 years ago therefore potentially falsifying the “Anatolian hypothesis”. However, DNA studies did support it with a common ancestral population to Indo-European speakers dated around 9000 years ago. Also on the DNA side, no clear evidence for population dispersion was available for supporting a later origin and faster spread of the proto-Indo-European (the “steppe hypothesis”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that was only until this month: a recent paper by Haak along with his 39 co-authors preprinted in &lt;a href=&quot;http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2015/02/10/013433&quot;&gt;BioRxiv&lt;/a&gt; provides evidence for a common ancestral population that originated in the Ukraine and spread at into northern and western Europe. This population links in space and time with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yamna_culture&quot;&gt;Yamnaya culture&lt;/a&gt; around 4000-5000 years ago suggesting that Yamnaya was close to the proto-Indo-European culture. Even though if the ‘Anatolian hypothesis’ cannot be excluded, this new paper strongly suggests that at least the European branch of the Indo-European language originated from the Yamnaya culture (see Extended Data Figure 5 p.32 and its legend p.27 of the preprint pdf for a &lt;a href=&quot;http://biorxiv.org/content/biorxiv/early/2015/02/10/013433.full.pdf&quot;&gt;nice visual summary&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore it is likely enough that Yamnaya was the origin of most European languages and that it spread rapidly through northern and western Europe probably due to technical advancements in transport. I find evolutionary linguistic always amazing when you can state that you wrote/read a blog post in a derived Yamnaya language: English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: wikimedia commons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2015/03/13/do-you-speak-yamnaya/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Do-you-speak-Yamnaya/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Do-you-speak-Yamnaya/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The more the better?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/birds-of-paradise-300x200.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot; /&gt;
These days I’m writing up the discussion of my sensitivity analysis paper on missing data using the Total Evidence method (more about it &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/10/06/phd-pretty-huge-disaster/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/10/13/phd-positive-happy-developments/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). One evident opening for proposing future improvement on my analysis is the obvious “let’s-do-it-again-with-more-data” one… But a recent &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/346/6215/1320.abstract&quot;&gt;Science paper&lt;/a&gt; by Jarvis et al made me reconsider that. Is more the always better?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jarvis and his numerous colleagues just published one of the biggest bird phylogenies that contrasts with the previous reference one (by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v491/n7424/abs/nature11631.html&quot;&gt;Jetz et al in Nature&lt;/a&gt;). In Jetz’s paper, the authors were interested in the relations among modern birds (read “non-dinosaurs ones”) and tackled the question by trying to sample the whole of bird biodiversity (9,993 species!). However, as in most analyses of this kind, the molecular data can be fairly poor (note that they still managed to collect a maximum of 15 genes for 6663 species). Even though the global picture of avian diversity is clear, some regions are less resolved than others and an obvious way to fix that would be to sample more genes per species. And that is, in a way, exactly what Jarvis and his colleagues tried to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this new study, the authors went on sampling not 15, 70 or 150 genes but 8251 genes per species! This led to a really deep and long analysis – over 400 CPU years, and I thought 150 was long! – of the complete genome of birds. By the way, they use the name Total Evidence nucleotide tree (TENT) to design the results of their analysis which is pretty confusing since a total evidence tree means &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/01/13/a-brave-new-world-of-monkeying-around-with-trees/&quot;&gt;something quite different&lt;/a&gt; to me. But that’s just a semantic rant. Using this massive TENT, the authors fixed some previously poorly resolved nodes, redefined the names of ancient divergences among birds (with the Passerea – tits and relatives – and the Columbea – pigeons and relatives), demonstrated an explosive (“big-bang”) radiation after the K-T event and determined the patterns of certain traits evolution (such as raptoriality or vocal learning). In short a thorough work that allowed the authors to say: “The conflict we observe with other data types can no longer be considered to be due to error from smaller amounts of sequence data”. I feel that writing something like that in a paper is a nice achievement!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However – don’t get me wrong, this paper is yet a great example of collaborative work and insight in new methods – the sample size is… 45 species. In other words, Jetz et. al sampled 100% of the species but less than 1% of the data as for Jarvis et al., they sampled 100% of the data for less than 1% of the species. In this case, we have two extreme views of the same question (“how did avian diversity evolve?”) and in both cases, I think the macroevolutionary claims are weakened by the number of species or the amount of data… However, from a practical point of view, I think the method that included more species will be preferred by researchers since their species of interest are more likely to be present in that tree. What’s the best balance? Full genome or full sampling? I’ll leave it to you to decide…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: http://everythingbirdsonline.com/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2015/02/06/the-more-the-better/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 06 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/The-more-the-better/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/The-more-the-better/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ecology of religious beliefs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Leese_CRU-T-shirt_09-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot; /&gt;
It is well known that your country of birth has a big influence on your religious outlook. That’s why Ireland is dominated by Christians whereas Iran has a mostly Muslim population. Your scientific outlook doesn’t escape from this either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, it’s arguable that the idea of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/02/03/levels-of-selection/&quot;&gt;group selection&lt;/a&gt; is viewed much more favourably in the US than the UK. Turning back to religion, a group of authors have recently carried out a study on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnas.org/content/111/47/16784.abstract&quot;&gt;ecology of religious belief&lt;/a&gt;. In their work they were able to predict the societies that believe in moralising high Gods by drawing on historical, social and ecological data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we’re in the beginning, we need a definition, so what exactly is a moralizing high God? These are “supernatural beings believed to have created or govern all reality, intervene in human affairs, and enforce or support human morality”. Supernatural belief has had a number of ecological correlates associated with it and this study points to environmental instability as one major driver. An environment with an unpredictable spatial or temporal distribution of resources lends itself to cultivating cooperation among the animals found within it. Among humans this results in a “reduction in cheating, increased fairness, and a tendency to cooperate”. And this is a fertile ground for the development of religious belief. One conclusion is that cultures in close proximity or those that share a common language exhibit similar religious beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the authors nuance this statement that this form of religion is being driven as a response to environmental harshness. In fact, they note that for societies living in a really harsh environment like the Inuits, variations tend to lead to more positive periods rather than negative ones and this seems to inversely correlate with the probability of believing in these type of gods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One ironic point however (largely discussed in &lt;a href=&quot;http://whyevolutionistrue.wordpress.com/2014/11/18/the-ecology-of-faith-what-makes-societies-religious/&quot;&gt;Jerry Coyne’s blog post&lt;/a&gt;), is that this paper is also influenced by the authors’ societal framework: a society traditionally believing in a god that they consider as moral and improving human lives. Taking that into account, some parts of the methodology heavily influence the results. The definition of morality by the authors and its benefits on humans as a species are highly depend on the societal framework where one is born. The “reduction in cheating, increased fairness, and a tendency to cooperate” is traditionally seen as a “good” thing for humanity in Abrahamic religions. Making it a universal or biological “right” behaviour is only the authors’ point of view (and probably one of &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyevolutionistrue.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/screen-shot-2014-11-18-at-7-33-18-am.png?w=565&amp;amp;h=167&quot;&gt;their funding agencies&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: http://mattleese.blogspot.ie/2009/12/we-dont-know-if-jesus-ever-rode-them.html&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2015/01/13/ecology-of-religious-beliefs/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; co-written with Adam Kane&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Ecology-and-religious-believes/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Ecology-and-religious-believes/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Say &quot;the rise of the age of mammals&quot; again, I double dare you!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/save-300x276.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot; /&gt;
In biology and among biologists, we like to use terms that we know are not correct but that still come in handy when you’re confident that your interlocutor understands them the way you do. I’m thinking of terms such as “key adaptations”, “living fossils”, etc… However, among them, there is one that particularly bugs me and makes me feel like Samuel L. Jackson in the iconic &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yvEik9N_xWI&quot;&gt;Pulp Fiction scene&lt;/a&gt; and that is: “the rise of the age of mammals”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, Barry Lovegrove and his students published a nice &lt;a href=&quot;http://rspb.royalsocietypublishing.org/content/281/1796/20141304.abstract&quot;&gt;data driven paper&lt;/a&gt; in Proceedings of the Royal Society B on the hibernation of tenrecs. The team found that these amazing creatures (I refer you to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/?s=Sive+Finlay+tenrec&quot;&gt;Sive’s posts&lt;/a&gt;, our tenrec expert) do go into hibernation for 9 months straight even though they live in tropical latitudes. The paper first sparked my curiosity because of this new tenrec fact but also due to the spin that the authors put on the paper’s results. They create a broad significance for the implications of their research on hibernation in tenrecs by describing their potential applications for how we might biologically programme astronauts to hibernate on a journey to Mars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what struck me the most (and I’m coming to main point of this blog post) is that the authors place their paper in the context of our understanding of the K-T boundary event which, they argue, was a key event in the evolutionary radiation of placental mammals (according to work by O’Leary and colleagues discussed &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/02/18/palaeo-poetry-and-placental-mammals/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/02/18/palaeo-poetry-and-placental-mammals/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). And from there, the authors claim that tenrecs’ “predation-avoidance  hibernation may be an ancient plesiomorphic characteristic in mammals and is a legacy, perhaps, of the 163 Myr of ecological suppression by the dinosaurs. It enabled the ancestral placentals, as well as the marsupials and monotremes […], to endure the short- and long-term devastations of the K-Pg asteroid impact, a capacity which is possibly the sole explanation for the existence of mammals today.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This suggestion is based solely on their findings about hibernation in tenrecs. Their rather crude extrapolations to what these results tell us about the origin of placental mammals are mainly based on two erroneous assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(1) they “report a plesiomorphic (ancestral) capacity for long-term hibernation that exists in an extant, phylogenetically basal, tropical placental mammal, the common tenrec”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(2) “The long ca. 160 Myr stint of the nocturnal, small, insectivorous mammal was over, and gave way to the age of the mammals, the Cenozoic” because of the “Ecological release from the vice grip which the dinosaurs held over Mesozoic mammals”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(1) Tenrecs are &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Afrotheria&quot;&gt;Afrotherians&lt;/a&gt;. They are a sister group of golden moles and nested somewhere within the elephant shrews and aardvarks clade that is sister to the elephants, hyrax and sirenians (so, even within Afrotherians, tenrecs are not particularly basal). Afrotherians are a sister group to either Xenarthrans or Boreoeutherians (depending on the genomic region) but all three together form the extant eutherians. It is mistaken to interpret tenrecs as a “basal” mammal clade. The authors claim that their “hibernation data show some affinities to the ‘protoendothermy’ first noted in echidnas, suggesting retention of plesiomorphic characteristics of hibernation on Madagascar through phylogenetic inertia”. This implies that this hibernation characteristic has been lost in all other mammal groups .Using basic principles of parsimony, it would make more sense to attribute this hibernation characteristic to being yet another example of a convergent trait in tenrecs, not an ancestral state which was lost in most other mammals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(2) I grew up reading a steady diet of books about the history of life. These presented a nicely summarized picture: around 65.5 Mya (now updated to 66 Mya, a small detail that can easily be fixed), all dinosaurs went extinct because they were too big and too stupid and the clever small mammals survived without any problem, liberated from their domination by the big stupid dinosaurs. This vision was awesome as a child; it had all the elements for a really anthropocentric/biblical view of the story (think about the &lt;em&gt;Exodus&lt;/em&gt;) and clearly explained why mammals are the dominant species today. It even explains the success of humans: we used our cooperation and intelligence to reach our dominant position as head of all the mammals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this romantic vision of the history of life (driven by paleontological data prior to the amazing discoveries of new Jurassic and Cretaceous mammals in the 90s and 2000s and the advent of molecular phylogenies) has, thankfully, been updated to integrate the last two decades of excellent work. This lead to a picture that is less romantic and more complex. The dinosaurs didn’t really disappear and are actually still more numerous (species richness-wise) than mammals nowadays. Similarly, the placental mammals and their ancestor didn’t just “bloom” after the K-T boundary event: they had their origin back in the late Jurassic, roughly at the same time as the dominant tetrapods of today (the birds), and they radiated multiple times: mainly due to global climatic changes during the Paleogene such as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eocene%E2%80%93Oligocene_extinction_event&quot;&gt;“Grande Coupure”&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paleocene%E2%80%93Eocene_Thermal_Maximum&quot;&gt;PETM&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure why the authors chose to adopt an outdated vision of the evolution of mammals to introduce their work but it seems a pity to me that such a spin is necessary to present good work on unknown/understudied groups even if they’re as cool as tenrecs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: http://www.smbc-comics.com/?id=1535&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/10/29/say-the-rise-of-the-age-of-mammals-again-i-double-dare-you/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Rise-of-mammals/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Rise-of-mammals/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PhD – Positive, Happy, Developments</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/RightOrWrong1921-225x300.png&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot; /&gt;
This post follows on directly from my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/10/06/phd-pretty-huge-disaster/&quot;&gt;previous discussion&lt;/a&gt; of my PhD going wrong. As a brief summary of the previous episode: I ran time consuming simulations that took me around 6 month to design and another 6 months to run. The simulation failed in the end because of a bug in some of the software I was using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I had to run them all over again!  That took me one day (at least to relaunch it, the simulations are actually still running). In this post I’d like to focus on the importance of starting to enforce good habits in using computers from the start of your PhD, whether you’re doing bioinformatics or field ecology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coding facilitates life. A lot. If I could only offer two tricks to remember they would be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Writing function-based scripts:&lt;/strong&gt; which involves isolating functions (the bits that are actually doing stuff) from scripts in order to be able to reuse/modify them easily for further/new analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Using version control:&lt;/strong&gt; which involves saving your work as you modify it and keeping a good track of the history so that when something goes wrong you know exactly which one was the last version that worked and which is the version that bugs.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are loads of other good tips and many excellent blogs about how to start good coding habits (for example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://nicercode.github.io/&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://software-carpentry.org/blog/index.html&quot;&gt;that one&lt;/a&gt;) so I am not going to develop the point here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll just try to make the point by using a philosophical-historical-dodgy example that convinced me to start coding. Coding is like using a printing press vs. a pencil to write a sentence: &lt;em&gt;I can write this sentence of 71 characters in approximately 16 seconds&lt;/em&gt;. And that is, with a pencil. If I had to use a printing press, it would take me one second to input each character in the press (assuming I trained a lot) plus one seconds for actually pressing the sentence. So that’s 16 seconds with a pencil and 72 seconds using the printing press (4.5 times longer). If you’re not that old-school, you will use a computer to analyse your data and what often happens is that it will take you less time to do things “by hand” (e.g. modifying column names, removing rows with NAs, etc…) than to write fancy functions. So why bother?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well it’s the same as using the printing press, if you just want to write the sentence once, then, sure, don’t bother, but if you need to write it 10 times? The writing would take 160 seconds and the printing takes only 81! Also you’re likely to make typos when copying the sentence with a pencil, but you won’t make any with the press!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the same applies to your computer analysis. If you’re removing columns with NAs “by hand” it will probably take you less time than writing a function. But what if you have more tables? How can you be sure you didn’t miss any? And on the plus side, if you write function-based scripts, chances are that you already have a function that does remove the columns with NAs from a former analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To follow up with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/10/06/phd-pretty-huge-disaster/&quot;&gt;my previous post&lt;/a&gt;, applied, to me, this happened to be a salvation! Because I spent 6 months trying to apply bioinformatics good practice, it only took me one day to relaunch the whole analysis! I just had to change the name of the version of the software that was bugged and press enter…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of doing actual science (i.e. from coming up with an interesting idea to submitting the paper) is not a continuous and straight process and it can drastically change at every step and is more about trial and error than about succeeding straight off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: wikimedia commons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/10/13/phd-positive-happy-developments/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Positive-Happy-Developments/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Positive-Happy-Developments/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>PhD – Pretty Huge Disaster</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Dresden-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;headimg&quot; /&gt;
This is a mini series of two posts about finding positive things in negative results. Science is often a trial and error process and, depending on what you’re working with, errors can be fatal. As people don’t usually share their bad experiences or negative results beyond the circle of close colleagues and friends, I thought (and hope!) that sharing my point of view, as a PhD student might be useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re about to do a PhD &lt;strong&gt;you will fail&lt;/strong&gt; and if you’ve already successfully finished one, &lt;strong&gt;you have failed&lt;/strong&gt;. At least a little bit… come on… are you sure? Not even a teeny tiny bit? By failure, I just mean scientific failure here, as if you ran an experiment and the result was… a fail, no results, do it again. There are millions of ways to fail, from errors in the experimental design to clumsiness but in this series of posts, I want to emphasize the consequences of failure more than its causes. I think that it is an important thing to learn and to embrace as a young future scientist, as much as journal rejection and other annoying and common silent academic failures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the two first years of my PhD, I went from the idea of quickly testing some assumptions as a starting point for a bigger question to some detailed and time consuming simulations on a detailed part of these assumptions. The time spent appeared to be completely useless scientifically because the analysis failed leading to false negative results and kept me away from going back to the bigger question. Or did it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When wrong is right part 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the summer of last year, I was working on an intensive computational project. I was running a kind of sensitivity analysis to see the effect of missing data on the phylogenies that have both living and fossil species (that’s called Total Evidence to link back to former posts, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/01/13/a-brave-new-world-of-monkeying-around-with-trees/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2013/03/29/dinosaurs-are-useless-if-they-dont-go-in-trees/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). In brief I was simulating datasets with a known (right) result by removing data from it to see how the results were affected. Because of my wide ignorance at the start in coding, simulations and the method I was testing, the project took way longer than planned. And all that was of course ignoring &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hofstadter%27s_law&quot;&gt;Hofstadter’s law&lt;/a&gt; (‘it always takes longer than you think, even when you take into account Hofstadter’s Law’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expected result, as for any sensitivity-like analysis, was that as you reduce the amount of data, the harder it would be to get the right results. That wasn’t what I found at all. Instead, my simulations seemed to be suggesting that whatever the amount of data, you never get the right results. Suspicious, I tried to check my simulations and asked advice from competent and talented people that helped me finding caveats in my project. But still, after checking and testing everything over and over again, the simulation results appeared to be the same: the amount of data doesn’t matter, the method just don’t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though these results were negative, they were intriguing and, if they were right, probably important because of the number of people willing to try the Total Evidence method over the last three years. From that perspective, I presented &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Bfr24VdYT8E&quot;&gt;my results&lt;/a&gt; at the Evolution 2014 conference in Raleigh. There, I got even more comments from even more people but still, the results appeared to be right. Until one person that had a similar unexpected result suggested that should try an older version of some of the software I was using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appeared that person was right and all the weirdness in the results that I tried for months to fix, check and explain were caused by a bug in the latest update (don’t use MrBayes 3.2.2 for Total Evidence analysis, prefer the version 3.2.1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After an obvious moment of relief, came an obvious negative feeling of having lost my time and how I should have given up instead of continuing to dig. But a posteriori, I’m actually glad of this misadventure and learned two really important lessons: (1) published software is not 100% reliable; always test their behaviour; (2) there is nothing more productive than sending your work to colleagues and experts for pre-reviewing. Even though, the bug appeared to be “trivial and easy to fix”, the amount of comments I had definitely helped improve both my understanding and my standards for this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photo credit&lt;/strong&gt;: wikimedia commons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecoevoblog.com/2014/10/06/phd-pretty-huge-disaster/&quot;&gt;Original post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Pretty-Huge-Disaster/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://TGuillermeBlog.github.io/Pretty-Huge-Disaster/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>